<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A compendious form and summe of Christian doctrine, called The testimonie of a true faith meete for well disposed families, for the more knowledge [in] God, and better nourishing vp, and confirming of all such, as loue saluation in Iesus Christ. Gathered, corrected, and newly augmented, by Christopher Shutte, Maister of Arte, seene and allowed.</title>
            <author>Shutte, Christopher, d. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22468</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100084</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835936</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835936</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12162)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1291:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A compendious form and summe of Christian doctrine, called The testimonie of a true faith meete for well disposed families, for the more knowledge [in] God, and better nourishing vp, and confirming of all such, as loue saluation in Iesus Christ. Gathered, corrected, and newly augmented, by Christopher Shutte, Maister of Arte, seene and allowed.</title>
                  <author>Shutte, Christopher, d. 1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Dawson, dwelling at the three Cranes in the Vinetree,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1579.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E⁴ h⁴(-h1,4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 22468.1 on UMI microfilm reel 1291.</note>
                  <note>Another edition, signed in full, of: Shutte, Christopher.  The testimonie of a true fayth.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology --  Miscellanea --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A compendious form and ſumme of Chriſtian doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, called the Teſtimonie of a true Faith, meete for well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed families, for the more knowledge in God, and better nouriſhing vp, and confirming of all ſuch, as loue ſaluation in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Gathered, corrected, and newly augmented, by Chriſtopher Shutte, Maiſter of Arte, Seene and allowed.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 34.11.</bibl>
               <p>Come ye children, hearken vnto me, I wil teach you the feare of the Lorde.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Thomas Dawſon, dwelling at the three Cranes in the Vinetree. 1579.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:171:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and his ſinguler good Lorde, <hi>George, Earle of Cumberland &amp;c.</hi> Chriſtopher Shutte wiſheth <hi>all increaſe of grace in the</hi> holie Ghoſt, &amp; long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of life in al hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie health and proſperity.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that I called to minde (Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable,<note place="margin">1. Re. 2.1. Pro. 4.1. 2. Re. 23.1.</note> and my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie good Lord) the diligent care, and prudent prouiſion, which Dauid and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good Princes and rulers of Iſrael had, for planting true religion in their Families, for their better conuerſation and good gouernement, according to the lawe and rule of faith: and had bene alſo often intreated and earneſtly inuited by ſome, my verie friendes, and ſuche as loue the ſaluation of the faithfull, to contract ſome compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Chriſtian forme of godlie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions
<pb facs="tcp:171:3"/> and ſweete prayers much re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quiſite in well diſpoſed families, whoſe godlie demaunde I was not willing to denie,<note place="margin">1. Luc. 214.</note> bothe becauſe I ſee the lacke thereof in manie families, to require ſo needefull a labour, and alſo, becauſe I woulde not abridge my duetie to my brethren and felowſhippe of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if it were but, with the poore wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, to caſt two mites into the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie: And waying alſo with my ſelfe, howe manie buſie braines are occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to quarrell without a cauſe with truth it ſelfe. I thought your honoures Godly Patronage to be a ſure aſyle, to ſupport and defende againſt the ſting of carping Zoilus, whatſoeuer in godly wiſe herein I ſhoulde propound. And therefore I haue boldlie preſumed too reſt vpon your Honoures hoped pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, as the chiefeſt anchore holde I had herein, and take effecte, to the ende my laboures might the better proceede. Whereto (my good Lorde) I was diuerſlie incenſed. Firſt by your Honoures good liking and procurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of good litterature from time to time whiche, neuer happened to anie
<pb facs="tcp:171:3"/> without deſerued prayſe and iuſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I was moued by your Honours good acceptation of my ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in the Lorde, and other good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunces towardes me, both of youre honour, vnto whome I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count my ſelfe moſt deepely indebted, and alſo of my good and moſt vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ladie, whom the Lorde hath ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as a moſte comfortable delight and helpe, vnto your honour. Whoſe faithfull ſocietie and happie felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, importeth an euident argument of Gods greate goodneſſe towardes you, in bleſſing you with the felowſhip of ſuch a one, as few or none excell or goe beyonde in trew godlineſſe, hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and vertue. To whom for her Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noures good affection to Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, I recogniſe my ſelfe muche bounde with all obedience.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I was prouoked herevnto, ſpecially, becauſe ſuch is and ought to bee the zeale and loue of all nobilitie, (whereof your honour is a moſt tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde Braunche) alwayes with maine and might, to defend the cauſe of true
<pb facs="tcp:171:4"/> Religion to the glorie of God, and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of his people, for whiche cauſe the Lorde hath ſtirred vp moſte noble men and godlie Magiſtrates, to be as Patrones, and protectoures to the Ambaſſadoures of his worde, for the better proceeding of religion. So he rayſed vp Moſes to Aaron, Ioſua to Eleazar, Dauid to Nathan, Aſa too Azariah, Iehoſaphat to Micha, Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias and others to Eſaie and Ieremie, Zerubbabel to Iehoſhua, and finally, the Emperoure Conſtantine to the councel of Nice. All which were right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie termed Nobles, for the zeale and loue they had to true religion. And albeit, by ſiniſter and crooked meanes ſome were ennobled, and ſo crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the carefull chaire of worldlie dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, yet none were euer rightly and in verie deede accompted noble, but ſuch as vndertooke the patronage and aide of Chriſtian religion, which thing I humblie craue vpon your Honoure. For euen in this wiſe,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.4.</note> Moſes doth call the Iſraelites a pretious and a noble ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neration, ſo long as they obſerued the commaundements of the Lord. Vpon
<pb facs="tcp:171:4"/> the like condition,<note place="margin">Pſal. 89. &amp;. 132.</note> the Lord eſtabliſhed his mercies with king Dauid his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt: that the throne of Iuda ſhould not be deſtitute of one to raigne vpon the ſame for euer.<note place="margin">1. Reg. 2.1.</note> To which thing Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid had reſpect, when he lay vppon his death bedde, and therevpon councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Salomon his ſonne, (to whom the kingdome was promiſed,) to walke in the way of truth, wherein he had bene brought vp: to the ende he might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper and haue good ſucceſſe.<note place="margin">Fox Pag 125</note> To like purpoſe, Romanus a man of great no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, being caried to the place of martirdom for the profeſſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion, (a rare thing in Nobles to beholde) boldely auouched, that his nobilitie reſted not ſo much in the bloude of his Aunceſtoures, as in the profeſſion of the Chriſtian faith, and other vertues thereto agreeing. And therefore he ſaide, <hi>Non progenitorum ſanguis, ſed Chriſtianae pietatis profeſſio me nobilem facit,</hi> that is, Not the bloud of my progenitoures, but the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſtian religion, maketh me noble and renowned.<note place="margin">Rom. 11.17.</note> And in deede if we ſhoulde with a ſingle eye, looke to
<pb facs="tcp:171:5"/> the Proſapie of Adam,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.23.</note> and wild oliue tree, out of the which all fleſhe was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, there woulde be no great cauſe of triumph to anie, of any thing whiche wee haue of nature:<note place="margin">Ro. 6.5. &amp;. 8.15 16.</note> But this is and ought to be manns chiefe nobilitie, that he is graffed in Chriſte Ieſus by faith, adopted to be the child of God, made by faith pertaker of his graces,<note place="margin">Theodorit. lib. 5. ca. 17.</note> and felow heire of his kingdome, and this is very nobilitie. Wherewith Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> beeing moued, aduertiſed the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> (and in him all nobilitie) to conſider his nature to bee fraile, leaſt happilie principallitie ſhoulde blinde him, and make him quite forget himſelfe, and his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towardes God.</p>
            <p>Wherevpon, it may be gathered (right honorable) that not onelie the Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates of al ſortes, ought well to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their calling, but ſpecially, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe them ſelues in all obedience, to ſerue the Lorde, to foſter his churche, to promote and defende his true religion: For therefore are they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to nobilitie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.11. Iſa. 49.23.</note> wherein, I woulde to God it might well pleaſe euen all de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>grees
<pb facs="tcp:171:5"/> of ſuche as bee exalted on highe and gouernoures of families, deepely to acknowledge and confeſſe, that the Lord hath made them Fathers for his trueth, Patrones to mainteine religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and lightes of godlie life for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to followe. For, like as the ſonne in the firmament,<note place="margin">Plato.</note> giueth light to all the regions rounde about him, and by his bright appearing expelleth the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, comforteth and cheereth the worlde: Semblably, ſhoulde nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie baniſh ſinne and corrupt religion, and be a lantern of Godlie life to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte and ſhine to others, that they mighte directe their liues after their good enſamples,<note place="margin">Phillip 2.15.</note> as the Apoſtle wiſheth the godlie to bee without rebuke, in the middeſt of a naughtie and croked generation, among whom they ſhould ſhine as lightes in the worlde. For as the Philoſopher <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, ſuche as the Heades and Rulers be, ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie bee the reſt of the common multitude.<note place="margin">Iſocrates</note> Vpon the which conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the <hi>Athenians</hi> Oratour <hi>Iſocrates</hi> wiſheth all men of nobilitie, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their liues, as a paterne for others,
<pb facs="tcp:171:6"/> to follow, knowing, that the manners of a whole towne or countrie doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the wayes and dooinges of the higher ſorte.<note place="margin">Lib. 3. Ca. 1.</note> To the like ende ſayeth Enagrius in the eccleſiaſticall hiſtories. that the life of a noble man ſhoulde be an image of vertue, for his ſubiectes to follow,<note place="margin">Contra Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtas.</note> that they might the ſooner bee allured to vertue and godlineſſe. Thus Sainte Auguſtine ſaieth, that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ought to ſerue GOD, not onelie in liuing godlie and modeſtlie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but alſo in bringing others to vertue and true Religion. Thus it was ſaide to Arcadius the Emperour, that godlineſſe was ſufficient to the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the noble men, without the whiche their Pompe and outwarde ſtrength was nothing woorth. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon (my verie good and vertuous Lorde) I may conclude and define with Sozomenus,<note place="margin">Sozo. lib. 9. Cap. 1.</note> that godlineſſe or loue of true Religion,<note place="margin">Lib. 1. Ca. 1.</note> is the greateſt honour and renowne of true nobilitie. And therefore as Conſtantine ſaide ſometimes to Sapors king of Perſia,<note place="margin">Theodorit. lib. 1. Ca. 25.</note> ſo ſay I to all ſuch of high degrees, which feare the Lorde: like as in keeping of
<pb facs="tcp:171:6"/> the ſacred faith, they are pertakers of the light of truth: ſo in following the light of truth, as a guide, they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſtraight to the ſacred faith: which thing may well inkindle in the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and zealous hearts of noble men and all others a feruent minde, to the imbracing and ſpreading abroade of true religion.<note place="margin">Niceph. lib. 4. Ca. 34.</note> And euen as Cyprian let no day paſſe, without the reading of Tertulian: nor Alexander without the reading of Homer: nor finally, Apelles without ſome line proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: ſo were it meete that no degrees, ſhoulde loſe anie opportunitie or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion graunted to the meditation of Chriſtian religion: but rather being taught by the example of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Conſtantine, woulde repoſe their whole ſtudie in the word of God And as for other things in the worlde, they are but vanitie and vexation of ſpirite. For all fleſh is graſſe,<note place="margin">Eccle. 1. Iſa. 40.6.</note> and all the glorie of man is as the flowre of the fielde, which ſtandeth beautifull to day, but tomorow is cut downe, dried vp, and withered. And what harme were it then, if ſome good man would put all
<pb facs="tcp:171:7"/> degrees in minde, as the <hi>Macedonian</hi> did <hi>Phillip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 2.16.</note> and ſay: remember man, that thou art but mortall, and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is in the worlde, but the luſte of the fleſh,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.31. 2. Cor. 5.10.</note> the luſt of the eyes and pride of life, &amp; that the figure of this worlde vadeth faſt away, that wee muſt alſo all appeare before the tribunall ſeate of God, that euerie one may render an accompt for that which he hath do ne in the bodie, be it good or euill. Were it not a meanes, to make euerie one more watchefull in his office? wherein than ought mans delight to be? ſurely as the Prophete ſaith: Let not the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man glorie in his wiſedome, nor the ſtrong man in his ſtrength,<note place="margin">Iere. 9.23.</note> nor the riche man in his riches: but let him that reioyceth, reioyce in this, that he vnderſtandeth and knoweth me: For I am the Lorde, whiche ſhewe mercie, iudgement,<note place="margin">Eccle. 11.9.10. &amp;. 12.2.</note> and righteouſneſſe in the earth, for in theſe thinges I delight, ſaith the Lorde. To the like purpoſe, is the good and wholſome counſel of the Preacher, Reioyce (O young men) ſaith he, in thy youth, and let thy hearte cheere thee, in the dayes of thy youth,
<pb facs="tcp:171:7"/> and walke in the wayes of thine heart, and in the ſight of thine eyes, but knowe that for all theſe thinges, God wil bring thee to iudgement: therefore take away griefe out of thine hearte, and cauſe euill, to departe from thy fleſhe: for childehoode and youth are vanitie. Remember now thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth, whiles the euill dayes come not, nor the yeares approche, wherein thou ſhalt ſay, I haue no pleaſure in them. O woulde to God that this godlie counſel might preuaile in princelie and noble hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and in euerie high and low degree, and eſpecially in heades of houſholdes, which beſt beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth their perſonages: Than woulde they enquire after the Lorde, and make his trueth, their cheife delight, and lay a ſure foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the way of righteouſneſſe, than ſhoulde this bee their ioy and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph: To knowe the Lorde to be their GOD, and themſelues to be his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to haue the teſtimonie of a good conſcience. Than ſhoulde they make anſweare to their obedience rightlie to the woorde of GOD,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.</note> than
<pb facs="tcp:171:8"/> ſhoulde they doe the dueties of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and loyall ſubiectes, and ſatiſfie her Maieſties deſire. Finally, than woulde they tender the ſtate of Churche and common weale, and ſhew themſelues carefull for the ſaluation of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>And becauſe there is no good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning for the accompliſhing of theſe things, but in the wiſedome, feare, and knowledge of the Lorde, the ſeede whereof is ſowen in your honoures heart, to my great comforte and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie hope of helpe, that your honoure will ſet forwarde and mainteine the trueth of Ieſus Chriſt in this poore countrie, and Labirinth of ignorance &amp; ſinne, I here moſt humbly commend vnto your honoures godlie zeale, a ſhorte forme of Chriſtian Religion, and godlie gouernement, moſt meete in wel diſpoſed families to be obſerued. Wherein is to be ſcene the ſumme of Chriſtian doctrine, faith, and godlie prayers, moſt meete for this our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eſtate: beſeeching your good Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure, in lieu of better, to accept the ſame in good parte, at my willing handes, recogniſing my ſelfe muche
<pb facs="tcp:171:8"/> bounden vnto your Honour, with all obedience for euer. And therefore knowing the knowledge of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to be the delight and comforte of the godlie,<note place="margin">Pſla. 119.24.105. Ro. 10.8. Iſa. 11.4. Iohn. 1027. 2. Cor. 2.16</note> the light vnto theyr pathes, the doctrine of faith vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, the ſcepter and protection of Gods kingdome, the marke and badge of Gods Elect, and ſauour vnto life, I here do preſent, the ſumme therof vnto your Lordſhip, in token of a thankefull remembraunce of youre Honoures courteſie towardes me, and in hope of fauourable acceptation thereof, Wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no leſſe vnto your Lordeſhip, then increaſe of all heauenlie graces and perfect happineſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the mediation of the Lord Ieſus: in whom I bid your Honour moſt hartely fare well.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your good Honoures moſt humble to commaund C. Shutte.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Teſtimonie of a trew</hi> faith, containing ſhort queſtions very neceſſarie to all Families <hi>for the more knowledge of God, and</hi> better bringing vp of children in his faith and feare.</head>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <head>1. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orſomuch as our Sauiour Chriſt in the Goſpel admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth his electe,<note n="a." place="margin">Matth. 6.33.</note> firſt to ſeeke the kingdome of God and the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes therof, and thereto adioyneth the promiſe of other, bleſſings to enſewe: I would gladly vnderſtand, howe the ſame might be perfourmed, which hee requireth ſo neceſſarily.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>There is no way ſo expedient to the atteyning of Gods heauenly graces, as to lay a good foundation of trewe religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the feare of God. Forasmuch as<note n="a." place="margin">Deut. 28. toto Pſal. 1.2.3.13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.15.22.</note> obedience to the Lawe of God, is
<pb facs="tcp:171:9"/> he readieſt &amp; onely way, to the fountaine of all perfect happineſſe. And for this cauſe<note n="b." place="margin">Deut. 6.6. 2. Sam. 6.11 Reg. 2.3. Act. 4.23. Luke. 19.9.</note> the godly men of all ages, proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alwaies from time to time, that they might nouriſh trew religion in their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, to the end, both they and theirs might be inſtructed better in the Lawe of God, and haue good ſucceſſe in thoſe thinges which they went about.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <head>2. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Doeſt thou than thinke, that thoſe houſholdes are diſordered, and not rightly ruled, where there is no dayly meditation of religion kept?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Such Families may rather be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a ſincke of ſinne, where the people are carefull of worldy profits and vaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, &amp; careles of the woord of God, and trewe religion.<note n="a." place="margin">1. Sam. 2.25.</note> And therefore they are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this caſe often times nearer to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="question">
               <head>3. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>How doeſt thou order and gouern thy houſe in Chriſtian religion.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a." place="margin">Deu. 6.6</note>As Moſes commaunded the people of Iſraell, to teach their children the
<pb facs="tcp:171:10"/> Lawe of the Lord, that in all their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires they might haue an eye vnto the ſame: ſo am I carefull, that my whole Familie feare God and know his woord by ſome dayly exerciſe, and meditation thereof. So as<note n="b." place="margin">1. Pet. 3.15.</note> they may be the better able to render a reaſon of their faith.<note n="c." place="margin">Act. 4.23.</note> They pray and geue thankes together in all their doinges.<note n="d." place="margin">Tit. 2.12.</note> They liue godlily, ſoberly and righteouſly.<note n="e." place="margin">Luke. 19.9</note> They make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, to whom they haue done wrong. And finally whatſoeuer they doo, they doo all to the glory of God,<note n="f." place="margin">Ioſ. 1.8.</note> and ſo they proſper, to God be praiſe therfore.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="question">
               <head>4. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Well than I pray thee ſhewe me the ſumme of that religion, which thou doeſt keepe in thy Familie? For it is the duetie of a true Chriſtian, alwayes to be ready<note n="a." place="margin">1. Pet. 3.15.</note> to render an account of his faith, to the ende it may appeare, that he is not<note n="b." place="margin">Mat. 10.32. Rom. 10.10.</note> aſhamed of Chriſt and his doctrine. Let me therefore heare what thou canſt ſay of the principall points of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>There be three ſpeciall partes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the firſt is<note n="a." place="margin">Iohn. 17.3. 2. Cor. 13.5.</note> to knowe God and my
<pb facs="tcp:171:10"/> elfe: the ſecond is,<note n="b." place="margin">Ioh. 5.24.</note> the meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by my ſaluation is wrought: the third,<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 6.9. and 26.26.</note> what helpes God doeth further me withall vnto life euerlaſting.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="question">
               <head>5. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What ſaieſt thou of the knowledge of God?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>The ſame is of two ſortes: the one is vniuerſall, and knowen<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 1.19. Pſal. 19.1.</note> by the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of heauen and earth, wherein God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth himſelfe to be ſeene and knowen of me, as the onely fountaine of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who alone<note n="b." place="margin">Deut. 6.13.</note> ought to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. For his<note n="c." place="margin">Gen. 1.1. Act. 17.24.</note> eternitie appeareth in the making of the world: his<note n="d." place="margin">Pſal. 36.</note> goodneſſe in preſeruing the ſame: his<note n="e." place="margin">Pſal. 107. Act. 17.28. Pſal. 115.3.</note> prouidence in the tokens which are ſeene and felt, wherby what pleaſeth his godly will commeth to paſſe, and not by blinde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: his<note n="f." place="margin">Pſal. 104.24</note> wiſedome in ordering of the thinges created: his<note n="g." place="margin">Rom. 2.7.8.9.10.</note> righteouſneſſe in deliuering the godly, and puniſhing the wicked: his<note n="h." place="margin">Ezec. 18.32</note> mercy in patiently for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing ſinners, and calling them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. So that what may be knowen of God, is manifeſt in the thinges crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which vniuerſall knowledge taketh
<pb facs="tcp:171:11"/> away<note n="i." place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note> all excuſe from the vngodly, which woorſhip not God aright: but to me, it is a<note n="k." place="margin">Pſal. 19.1.</note> ready way to bring me to the true worſhip of God.</p>
                  <p>The other knowledge is ſpeciall, and onely proper<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.3. Iere. 31.34.</note> to the elect, whereby, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row faith poured into my hart by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, I am aſſured that my ſaluation is wrought by Chriſt the ſonne of God: by whom<note n="m." place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> I am made the childe of God thorow grace, and heyre with Chriſt of his kingdome: which knowledge onely commeth of<note n="n." place="margin">Luke. 10.21</note> grace, and ſo is geuen to me, but it is reſtrained from the wicked, becauſe of their<note n="o." place="margin">Math. 13.14</note> ſinne and hardeneſſe of hart.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="question">
               <head>6. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What ſayeſt thou of the knowledge of thy ſelfe?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>By creation I was made in Adam, according to the<note n="a." place="margin">Gene. 2.27.</note> Image of GOD (I meane not any bodily ſhape, for God is a<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 4.24.</note> ſpirit, and without body) in true righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and holyneſſe,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.24.</note> that is to ſay, in al perfection and happineſſe of nature, both in right iudgement, reaſon, will and ſtrength. In which happy ſtate, if Adam
<pb facs="tcp:171:11"/> had continued, both I and all his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie had bene bleſſed for euer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="question">
               <head>7. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Howe dideſt thou fall from this grace.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>My fall appeareth, in that<note n="a." place="margin">Gene. 3. toto.</note> Adam who had this bleſſing for me, thorow the intiſement of the Serpent brake the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of God, in eating of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruite, and by the ſame depriued himſelfe of his former happineſſe, and brought ſinne, death, hell, the wrath of God, and all kinde of miſeries into the world,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> as iuſt puniſhmentes for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertes. In which his ſinfull act, his pride, diſobedience, lacke of faith, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefulneſſe to his creatour, and light credite to the Deuill appeared. In which offence, both I and al his ofſpringe are wrapped, in as much as in him wee all haue ſinned, for he had the bleſſing ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to keepe or looſe for him and his. Wherefore I and all others deſcending of him, by him, &amp; in him, haue fallen from grace, and are infected with his corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note n="b." place="margin">Pſal. 51.5.</note> conceyued in ſinne, borne in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and<note n="c." place="margin">Epheſ. 2.3.</note> by nature the children of
<pb facs="tcp:171:12"/> wrath,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.10.</note> and vtterly vndone, without the grace and mercy of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="question">
               <head>8. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What is mannes free will, his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſtrength, wiſedome, and ſuch lyke vertues loſt by this his fall in Adam, all which he had in the beginning?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Concerning mans will, before his fall the ſame was free, but afterward not ſo,<note n="a." place="margin">Iohn. 8.36.</note> but as the ſame is freed by grace. For<note n="b." place="margin">Pſal. 14.2.3</note> his iudgement is vnperfect and often deceiued, his will in many thinges hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and his ſtrength decayed,<note n="c." place="margin">Iohn. 3.5. &amp; 15.4. 2. Cor. 3.5. Phillip. 1.6. &amp;. 2.13.</note> that of himſelfe, he cannot perceiue the thinges which belong to the kingdome of God. So that as now to will aright is the gift of grace, ſo, to wil &amp; choſe amiſſe, is the lacke of grace: And yet this will of man not regenerate, in ſome reſpect may be termed free, becauſe<note n="d." place="margin">Eccle. 13.9.</note> a man doeth euill by his owne conſent, and not by compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And as for other his vertues and good giftes, which he had before his fall, lyke as in a ruinous houſe, there remaine certaines reliques of an houſe, although nothing comparable to their former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie: ſo after <hi>Adams</hi> fall, man not
<pb facs="tcp:171:12"/> egenerate<note n="e." place="margin">Iſa. 29.4. 1. Cor. 1.19. Ro. 8.7. &amp;. 10.3.</note> hath a certeine kinde of wiſedome, carnall knowledge, ſhewe of religion and holines, and yet the ſame ſo imperfect, both by his naturall corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; by the tyrannie of the Deuill, that<note n="f." place="margin">Iohn. 3.5.</note> till hee bee regenerate and ſanctified with grace from aboue, he can not pleaſe God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="question">
               <head>9. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Howe art thou reſtored to grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>My reſtauration commeth thorowe<note n="a." place="margin">Tit. 3.5. Ephe. 2.4.</note> the free mercy and fauour of God, who after this my fall in Adam, rayſed both him and me vp againe with the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table<note n="b." place="margin">Geneſ. 3.15 &amp;. 12.2. &amp;. 22 18.</note> promiſe of a Sauiour, who by his<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 3.25. Col. 1.22. 2. Cor. 5.21.</note> death ſhould pacifie the wrath of God, and bring me into his fauour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine:<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 5.19</note> by whoſe obedience I am made righteous: which my regeneration com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thus to me, whileſt<note n="e." place="margin">Matth. 3.2. Luke. 24.47.</note> by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Lawe, I am brought to the feeeling of my ſinnes, and rayſed vp with the comfortable promiſes of the Goſpel,<note n="f." place="margin">Act. 15.9. 1. Cor. 3.16.</note> receyued by faith. My harte is light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, purified, and gouerned by the holy Ghoſt:<note n="g." place="margin">Ephe. 4.24</note> my will and minde reformed, &amp; the Image of God renued againe in me.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:171:13"/>
               <head>10. <hi>Queſtion,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Why did God regenerate thee, and not raither get him ſelfe glory, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning thee according to thy ſinnes.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Although the Lorde<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 3.10. &amp; 9. toto. Deut. 7.8. Ezech. 36.22. Ioh. 15.16. Ephe. 2.4. 2. Tit. 1.9. Tit. 3.5</note> might iuſtly haue condemned all Adams poſteritie, by reaſon of their ſinnes, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſome of them according to his iuſt iudgementes, he leaueth in their owne corruption, deuoid of all grace, and Veſſels of his wrath vnto damnation: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſome he embraceth in his great loue vnto ſaluation, whome hee accepteth in mercy w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any deſerts of their own. Of which number, my conſcience dooth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me that I am one. And therefore he hath regenerate me,<note n="b." place="margin">Eph. 14.5. 1. Pet. 1.3. Iohn. 3.16. Rom. 8.29.30.</note> firſt to declare his great loue, mercy &amp; euerlaſting kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes towardes me, whom he choſe in his ſonne Chriſt to ſaluation. And therefore in an happie tyme, he hath called me by the preaching of his woord, and iuſtified me by my onely faith in Chriſtes death:<note n="c." place="margin">Matth. 5.16. Rom. 6. toto. Epheſ. 2.10. 2. Pet. 1.10.</note> Secondly, that I being thus borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe, may bring foorth the fruites of righteouſnes to glorifie him withall.<note n="d." place="margin">1 Pet. 1.3.4. Act. 26.18. Rom. 6.22.</note> Thirdly, that all the end of my regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:171:13"/> is life euerlaſting: ſo at the Lordes good time, I may receiue the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Saintes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="question">
               <head>11. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Shew me what be the meanes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thy ſaluation is wrought?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>The ordinarie meanes commonly are two, that is to ſay,<note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 24.47. Rom. 10.17.</note> the woorde of God, and faith.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="question">
               <head>12. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What is the woorde of God?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>It is thoſe Canonicall ſcriptures<note n="a." place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16 2. Pet. 1.21.</note> written by the ſpirite of God, &amp; commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to man both in the olde and newe Teſtament, wherein are conteined<note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 4.2. &amp; 12.32. Galat. 1.8. Luke. 16.29.</note> all thinges neceſſarie to our ſaluation, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the which, the Lord will haue all his religion meaſured, without either adding or diminiſhing.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="question">
               <head>13 <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>How canſt thou knowe the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, in ſo many ſundrie opinions of the ſame, as be in the worlde?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a." place="margin">Act. 17.11.</note>Firſt, I trie the religion taught me by the woorde of God, and by his ſpirite
<pb facs="tcp:171:14"/> geuen me to vnderſtande the ſame.<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.39.</note> Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>condly,<note n="b." place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.1.2.</note> I knowe this ſpirite to be a right ſpirit, becauſe it confeſſeth Chriſt to be come in the fleſhe, that is to ſay, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth the whole worke of my ſaluation to him, and to no other thing. Thirdly,<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 3.31.</note> I expounde one place of Scripture, as it is not contrarie to another. And thus I trie the truth,<note n="d." place="margin">Iohn. 12.48.</note> making the worde of GOD to iudge and determine what I ought to followe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="question">
               <head>14. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What is the cauſe why the word of God is preached to many, and yet ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth place but in few?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>The cauſes are manie,<note n="a." place="margin">Ro. 10.16. &amp; 11.7.</note> firſt manns owne diſobedience and contempt of the worde, through want of faith,</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="b." place="margin">2. Cor. 4.4.</note>Secondly, the malice of Sathan, who blindeth and hardeneth the hearts of the vnfaithfull, that they ſhoulde not ſee and beleeue the truth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="c." place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.11. Rom. 1.14. Apoc. 13.8. &amp;. 14.9.</note>Thirdly, the iuſt iudgement of God: Who, becauſe they refuſe to receiue and beleeue the truth, doth giue them vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a reprobate minde, and ſendeth ſtrong deluſion among them, that as they doe
<pb facs="tcp:171:14"/> delight in lies and <hi>m</hi> vnrighteouſneſſe, ſo the ſame may be their deſtruction.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="question">
               <head>15. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>How is the worde of GOD deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Into the<note n="a." place="margin">Mat 3.2. Luke. 24.47.</note> Lawe and the Goſpel.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="question">
               <head>16. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What is the Lawe.?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>It is the ten commaundementes of God, requiring of euerie one<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 27.26.</note> moſt pure perfect, and perpetuall obedience,<note n="b." place="margin">Leuit. 18.5. Rom. 10.5. Mat. 19.17.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing ſaluation to them which fulfill the ſame, threatning death and damnation to the tranſgreſſours thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="question">
               <head>17. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Rehearſe the ſame to me.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p n="1">1<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods but me.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen image, nor the likeneſſe of any thing that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth beneath, or in the waters vnder the earth: thou ſhalt not bowe downe to them nor worſhip them, for I the Lorde thy God am a ielous God, and viſiteth
<pb facs="tcp:171:15"/> the iniquities of the fathers vpon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren vnto the thirde and fourth generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them that hate me, and ſhewe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vnto thouſandes in them that loue me, and keepe my commaundementes.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thou ſhalte not take the name of the Lorde thy God in vaine, for the Lord will not holde him guilteles, that taketh his name in vayne:</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Remember that thou keepe holy the Sabboth day: ſixe dayes ſhalt thou labour and doe all that thou haſt to doe, but the ſeuenth day is the Sabboth of the Lorde thy GOD, in it thou ſhalt doe no manner of worke, thou, and thy ſonne, and thy daughter, thy man ſeruaunt, and thy mayd ſeruaunt, thy cattel, &amp; the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger within thy gates: for in ſixe dayes the Lord made heauen and earth, the ſea and all that in them is, and reſted the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day, wherefore the Lorde bleſſed the ſeuenth day, and hallowed it.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 Honour thy father and thy mother, that thy dayes may be long in the lande, which the Lord thy God geueth thee.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 Thou ſhalt not kill.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171:15"/>9 Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 Thou ſhalt not couet thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures houſe, thou ſhalte not couet thy neighboures wife, nor his ſeruaunt, nor his maide, nor his Oxe, nor his Aſſe, nor any thing that is his.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="question">
               <head>18. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What ſayeſt thou of the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>The Lorde therein requireth<note n="a." place="margin">1. Sa. 15.22. Deut. 10.12.</note> true obedience to his woorde, the feare and loue of his name,<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 3.15.16.</note> a ſure faith and truſt in his promiſes,<note n="c." place="margin">Pſal. 50.15. and 23.</note> the right inuocation vppon his name, with thankeſgeuing for his benefites, whereby his true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe may be knowen aright: whiche thinges as he doth commaunde, ſo doeth he forbidde<note n="d." place="margin">Deut. 4.15.</note> all manner of ſuperſtition and idolatrie,<note n="e" place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.8. 2. Tim. 4.4.</note> the contempt and denial of his woorde,<note n="f." place="margin">Rom. 3.18. Iacob. 2.14. 1. Iohn. 3.10.</note> the lacke of feare, faith and loue towardes him,<note n="g." place="margin">Apo. 13.6. &amp; 19.10. &amp;. 22.9.</note> calling vppon other creatures, and finally, whatſoeuer polluteth his ſeruice, or our conſciences in whoſe preſence all our doinges doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="question">
               <head>19. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:171:16"/>
               <p>What ſayeſt thou of the ſeconde? Thou ſhalt not make. &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>God doth therein declare how he wil be worſhiped. For ſeeing that his true worſhip<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 6.13. Rom. 14.23 Matth. 5.16.</note> is worke or ſeruice commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his woord, proceeding of faith, and tending to his glory; as he is a<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 4.24.</note> ſpirite, ſo he will be woorſhiped in ſpirit and truth, without<note n="c." place="margin">Leuit. 18.3 Deut. 7.25. &amp; 12.2. &amp;. 14.3.</note> any mixture of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie or ſuperſtition. And therefore he forbiddeth<note n="d." place="margin">Deut. 4.23 Eſay. 40.18.</note> the making of Images, to expreſſe him by<note n="e." place="margin">Exod. 34.14. Pſalm. 97.7.</note> all manner deuotion or reuerence geuing to them, eyther in looking at them, or in bowing the knee before them in prayer: he is the Lorde our God, and will not haue his power to be contemned:<note n="f." place="margin">Exod. 34.14 1. Cor. 11.2.</note> he is ielous ouer vs, and will not ſuffer eyther our ſoules or bodies to be defiled with any filthineſſe of Idolatrie: which if we doe, he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenenge the ſame to the third and fourth generation. Briefly he forbiddeth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by<note n="g." place="margin">Deut. 12.2.</note> all repreſentations and tokens of Idolatrie,<note n="h." place="margin">Eſay. 29.13.</note> all ſtraunge worſhip de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed by man,<note n="i." place="margin">Apoc. 13.15 and 14.9, &amp; 18 4.</note> all antichriſtian Decrees and whatſoeuer corrupteth the true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and ſpirituall woorſhip of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:171:16"/>
               <head>20. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What is commaunded in the third? Thou ſhalt not take. &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare</head>
                  <p>Herein the Lord commaundeth a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend vſe of his name,<note n="a." place="margin">Deut. 6.13.</note> truely to ſweare and teſtifie the truth, not<note n="b." place="margin">Ierem. 4.1.2</note> onely in truth, iudgement, and righteouſneſſe, but alſo<note n="c." place="margin">Ioſu. 2.12. 2. Cor. 1.23.</note> for neceſſities ſake, eſpecially when the glorie of God, and the ſaluation of our brethren is ſought: requiring alſo here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a faithfull zeale and<note n="d." place="margin">Deut. 6.5. Act. 2.42.</note> loue towardes his woord and Sacramentes, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer<note n="e." place="margin">1. Cor. 10.31</note> may ſet foorth his glory, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<note n="f." place="margin">Deut. 28.58.</note> the indiſcrete and vnreuerende vſe of his name in vaine and friuolous thinges, all raſh othes, all<note n="g." place="margin">Pſalm. 15.4.</note> othes made for fauour, lucre, and feare, rather than for triall of truth, all<note n="h." place="margin">Leuit. 19.12.</note> periury, all othes made<note n="i." place="margin">Deut. 10.21 Ierem. 5.17. Amos. 8.14.</note> by Saintes, Idolles, meate, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures,<note n="k." place="margin">Deut. 18.10</note> all coniurations, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries, Charmings, ſouth ſayings, witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft,<note n="l." place="margin">Ehpe. 4.31.</note> curſing and banning,<note n="m." place="margin">Rom. 16.17 Apoc. 14.9.</note> all falſe doctrines, and corruptions of true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and whatſoeuer<note n="n." place="margin">Rom. 2.24.</note> cauſeth the name of GOD to bee euyll ſpoken of.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="question">
               <head>21. <hi>Queſtion</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="question">
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171:17"/>
                  <p>as they obey his woorde, from whence when they decline,<note n="d." place="margin">Dan. 3.18. Act. 4.19.</note> they are no longer to be obeyed, forbidding alſo<note n="e." place="margin">Leuit. 20.9.</note> all diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and ingratitude of children tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes their parentes,<note n="f." place="margin">Num. 16. toto 2. Sa. 15. &amp;. 17.</note> all contempt and rebellion of ſubiectes againſt their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, alſo<note n="g." place="margin">Exod. 22.28</note> to blaſpheme them, and to<note n="h." place="margin">1. Reg. 14.16.</note> obey them in matters contrarie to the truth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="question">
               <head>24. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What canſt thou ſay of the ſixt, Thou ſhalt not kill?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>God in this commaundeth<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 5.23. Iohn. 13.34. Rom. 13.8. Epheſ. 4.2.31.</note> faithfull loue, mercie, kindeneſſe, compaſſion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilation, and mutuall embracing one an other in peace, aſwell of our enimies as of thoſe whiche loue vs, forbidding<note n="b." place="margin">Galat. 5.20 Epheſ. 4.31. 1. Cor. 3.1. and .10.10. Rom 13 8.9. 1. Iohn. 3.10.</note> all vnlawful murder and quarrelling out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardely, all fained loue, vnmercifulneſſe, hatred, malice, anger, reproches, tauntes, ſlaundering, murmuring, contentions, deſire of vengeance, and whatſoeuer is repugnant to Chriſtian loue.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="question">
               <head>25. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Proceede to the ſeuenth, Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171:17"/>
                  <p>The Lorde commaundeth not onelie<note n="a." place="margin">1. Cor. 6.15 1. Theſ. 4.4</note> perfect chaſtitie both in ſoule and bodie, whether it bee in marriage or in ſingle life, that all our parties may be ſanctified vnto him: but alſo he forbiddeth<note n="b." place="margin">Galat. 5.20 Apoc. 21.8.</note> all manner of adulterie and fornication,<note n="c." place="margin">1. Tim. 4.3 Eccleſ. 5.5</note> the reſtraining of lawfull mariage in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie calling, and the raſhe vowing of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle life,<note n="d." place="margin">Math. 5.28. Rom 6.12. and 7.7.</note> vnlawfulll luſtes,<note n="e." place="margin">Eſay. 3.16. 1. Ti. 2.9 1. Pet. 3.5.</note> light beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and vnſeemely adorning of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,<note n="f" place="margin">Ephe. 4.29. and .54. Colloſ. 4.6.7. Gal. 5.20.21.</note> filthie talke and idle paſtimes, dronkenneſſe, minſtrelſie, daunſing, and what beſides tendeth to impuritie and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous luſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="question">
               <head>26. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Declare the eight, Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Herein God commaundeth<note n="a." place="margin">Pſalm. 15.2. Tit. 2.12. Rom. 13.8</note> righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and true dealing in euerie cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and that euerie man be contente with his owne ſtate, geuing to euerie one what of right he ought to haue: forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding alſo<note n="b." place="margin">Ephe. 4.28. 1. Theſ. 4.6.</note> all robbing and falſehoode,<note n="c." place="margin">Luke. 12.15 Pſalm. 15.5. Prouer. 11.1.</note> couetuouſneſſe, vſurie, oppreſſion, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling with falſe meaſures,<note n="d." place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.10</note> i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle liuing,<note n="e." place="margin">Luke. 15.13.</note> vnhoneſt waſting of goodes or ſubſtance, and what elſe doth ſauoure
<pb facs="tcp:171:18"/> of deceite, the ſame is ſtealing.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="question">
               <head>27. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Shewe the ſence and meaning of the neinth? Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>God commaundeth herein,<note n="a." place="margin">Epheſ. 4.25. Iſai. 33.15.</note> in courte and iudgement, and in all our wordes and couenantes, that trueth may floriſhe, to ſaue our neighboures harmeleſſe,<note n="b." place="margin">Deut. 1.16. Iſai. 10.15.</note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding wrong iudgement, or anie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte of perſons therein, the making of wicked lawes and decrees, alſo<note n="c." place="margin">Deut. 19.16. Epheſ. 4.25. 1. Cor. 13. toto.</note> falſe witneſſe, and lying tales, flatterie, ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, falſe accuſations, and whatſoeuer impaireth the good name of our brethren.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="question">
               <head>28. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What ſaieſt thou of the laſt, Thou ſhalt not couet &amp;c?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>In this the Lorde commaundeth<note n="a." place="margin">Deut. 6.5. Matth. 22.37. Luke. 10.27.</note> the whole heart to be poſſeſſed with loue, that whatſoeuer man doth wiſh or deſire, may bee free from luſt and corrupt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and ſerue to the glorie of God, and profite of his neighboures, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hereby<note n="b." place="margin">Geneſ. 6.5. Matth. 5.28. Rom. 6.12.</note> all wicked thoughtes and vnlawfull deſires both of ſoule and bodie,
<pb facs="tcp:171:18"/> although our conſent be not thereto,<note n="c." place="margin">Ephe. 2.24.</note> all corruption of originall ſinne by Adam, all lacke of grace, and whatſoeuer wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of the integritie &amp; perfection where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in man was made. By all whiche pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes, it may appeare, that<note n="d." place="margin">Iob. 15.14. Deut. 27.26. Leuit. 18.5. Luke. 17.10.</note> nothing but true righteouſnes and innocencie can pleaſe God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="question">
               <head>29. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>By this I vnderſtande, that thou art not able of thy ſelfe,<note n="a." place="margin">Rom 8.3.</note> becauſe of thy ſinnes, to fulfil theſe lawes: why there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did God commaund that, which thou canſt not doo?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Firſt, hereby he declareth howe that his image in me<note n="a." place="margin">Epheſ. 4 23.24.</note> is corrupted with ſinne, for nothing is here required, which I coulde not haue done before my fall in Adam.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,<note n="b." place="margin">Deut. 27.26</note> here is nothing commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded which I am not bounde to do.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,<note n="c." place="margin">Deut. 6.25.</note> he doeth not reſpect what I of my ſelfe can doe, but what his iuſtice doth require. Laſt of all, it ſetteth foorth the<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 4.15. and .7.7.</note> wrath of God, and bringeth me to the feeling of my ſinnes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="question">
               <head>30. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:171:19"/>
               <p>Why, God is merciful to thouſands, &amp; will not ſurely puniſh ſinne ſo ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as thou thinkeſt.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a." place="margin">Exod. 20.6.</note>God in deede is mercifull to them that loue him, and truely repent, but he is a<note n="b" place="margin">pſalme. 7.6. and. 11.7. Deut. 32.35.</note> iuſt iudge, and a God of venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, to puniſh the wickedneſſe of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, which breake his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="question">
               <head>31. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>By this I gather, that many are in a wofull caſe.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Concerning the wicked, whiche bee voide of faith and of the mercie of God,<note n="a." place="margin">1. Tit. 1.9 Deut. 27.26</note> the curſe of the Lawe hangeth vppon them: But touching the elect, of which companie I am perſwaded that I am one,<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 3.16 2. Cor. 5.21. Rom. 3.25</note> Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God in myne owne nature hath ſuffred, to deliuer mee from ſinne, and the puniſhmentes thereof, and hath brought me into fauour of God againe, of whiche benefite I lay holde<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 1.16 Act. 15.11</note> with a true faith,<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 10.17</note> which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by the preaching of the Goſpell.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="question">
               <head>32. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What is the Goſpell?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171:19"/>
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>It is the<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 10.8</note> doctrine of faith,<note n="b." place="margin">Math. 11.28 Iohn. 5.24.</note> contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the promiſes of God vnto ſaluation,<note n="c." place="margin">Luke. 24.47. Iohn. 3.15. and 6.47.</note> to all which truely repent, and lay holde of Chriſtes merites, by a ſure truſt in the ſame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="question">
               <head>33 <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Why calleſt thou the Goſpell the doctrine of faith?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Firſt becauſe<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 10.17.</note> faith commeth, and is nouriſhed by the preaching of the Goſpel: Secondly<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 3.16</note> becauſe the promiſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, muſt be receiued onely by faith.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="question">
               <head>34. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What do the promiſes of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell meane:</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Firſt they teach me that the Lawe of God is fulfilled for me by Chriſt,<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 5.19. Ephe. 2.15 Galat. 3.13.</note> by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue my ſinnes forgiuen, and with<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30 2. Cor. 5.21.</note> whoſe righteouſneſſe I am clothed, and may now boldely ſtand before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate of God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly that my ſaluation<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 3.24. and .4.5.16.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth onely of the free mercie of God, without my merites or good deedes.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly<note n="d." place="margin">Matt. 22.14.</note> although they be offred to
<pb facs="tcp:171:20"/> all, yet they take effect in none to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but onely in the elect, whoſe hearts GOD lighteneth with faith.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="question">
               <head>35. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Shewe me what faith is.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>There is a kinde of faith, called<note n="a." place="margin">Iames. 2.14. Act. 8.13.</note> a deade fayth, beleeuing the woord of God to be true, and all thinges therein contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and goeth no farther: but the true faith is<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 17.3.</note> the ſure knowledge of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly good will and mercy of God ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towardes man in Chriſt,<note n="c." place="margin">Epheſ. 3.17.</note> and a ſure truſt in the ſame, whiche<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 6. toto.</note> in due tyme bringeth forth the fruites of good liuing.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="question">
               <head>36. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What doeſt thou learne hereby?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Firſt I learne to know God, who is made<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> my Father by Chriſt, thorowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption and grace.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly,<note n="b." place="margin">Galat. 2.20.</note> I applie to my ſelfe by this my faith, al the merites of Chriſt as fully, as if I had doone the ſame my ſelf.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly,<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 4.19. Hebr. 4.16. and 10.22.</note> I haue a ſure truſt in his merites and mercy, and boldnes to offer vp my prayers to GOD the father by him.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb facs="tcp:171:20"/>4 Laſt of all I knowe his promiſes to<note n="d." place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> be faithfull and true, and that he will perfourme them, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it pleaſeth his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſedome.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="question">
               <head>37. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Whence commeth faith?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>It is the gift<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 11.25 27. &amp;. 13.11. Act. 16.14. Rom. 12.6 Galat. 5.22. Ephe. 2.8</note> of GOD, wrought in my hart by the preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="question">
               <head>38. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What is the ſumme of faith?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>I beleeue in God the father almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, maker of heauen and earth, and in Ieſus Chriſt his onely ſonne our Lorde, which was conceiued by the holy Ghoſt, borne of the Virgin Mary, ſuffred vnder Poncius Pilate, was crucified, deade, and buried, he deſcended into Hell, and roſe againe the third day from the deade, he aſcended into heauen, and ſitteth on the right hand of God the father almightie: from thence he ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the deade. I beleeue in the holy Ghoſt: the holy catholike Churche, the communion of ſaintes, the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſinnes, the reſurrection of the body and the life euerlaſting.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:171:21"/>
               <head>39. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What art thou taught hereby?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Firſt, what to beleeue of God my father and creatour:</item>
                     <item>2 Secondly, of Chriſt my redeemer:</item>
                     <item>3 Thirdly, of the holy Ghoſt my ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifiour: Laſt of all, concerning the church of God:</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="question">
               <head>40. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What canſt thou ſay of God?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>God is<note n="a." place="margin">Iohn. 4.24</note> a ſpirituall nature,<note n="b." place="margin">Rom. 16.26.</note> euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,<note n="c." place="margin">Sam. 45.5.6.7. Rom. 3.4</note> almightie,<note n="d." place="margin">Pſalm. 139.7.8.9.</note> infinite,<note n="e." place="margin">Pſalm. 119.137.</note> true,<note n="f." place="margin">Matth. 19.17</note> good<note n="g." place="margin">Pſalm. 11.7.</note> righteous, and mercifull,<note n="h." place="margin">Exod. 34.6.</note> who hath made the worlde, and<note n="i." place="margin">Geneſ. 1.1</note> hath begotten the Sonne of himſelfe from euerlaſting.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="k." place="margin">Iohn. 1.1.</note>The ſonne is the<note n="l." place="margin">Prouer. 8.23 Hebr. 1.3. Apoc. 1.8.</note> wiſdome and image of the father, begotten of the father, very God of very God,<note n="m." place="margin">Iohn. 1.14. Galat. 4.4.</note> who, in his time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, became man.</p>
                  <p>The holie Ghoſt is<note n="n." place="margin">Iohn. 14.16 26.</note> the power and vertue proceeding from them both, which three, although they be<note n="o." place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h. 3.16 27.</note> diſtinct in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons yet are they<note n="p." place="margin">Deut. 4 6.</note> equal &amp; al one in God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,<note n="a." place="margin">Iohn. 1.1. &amp; .5.18.21. 1. Iohn. 5.7</note> eternitie, dignitie, and power.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="question">
               <head>41. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What ſayeſt thou of the firſt parte
<pb facs="tcp:171:21"/> of this faith?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>I beleeue, that God is not onely the<note n="a." place="margin">Math. 3.17 Rom. 8.16.</note> naturall father of his ſonne Chriſt, but alſo that he is by grace my father, by whoſe wiſedome as heauen and earth, and all things therin conteined, were made, ſo the ſame by his<note n="b." place="margin">Pſalm. 145.15. Heb. 1.3. Mat. 10.28.</note> power is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned and preſerued.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="question">
               <head>42. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What thinkeſt thou of the ſecond?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>I beleeue that<note n="a." place="margin">Heb. 5.15.</note> the ſonne of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came man, in all thinges like vnto me, onely ſinne excepted, and in my nature wrought what was needefull to my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,<note n="b." place="margin">Matth. 1.21. Act. 4.12.</note> wherefore he is named Ieſus, that is, a Sauiour.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="question">
               <head>43. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>How is thy ſaluation wrought.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>This woord Chriſt, doth teach the ſame, for firſt it ſignifieth him to be a king, and to haue purchaſed to him ſelfe<note n="a." place="margin">Act. 20.28. Luke. 1.33.</note> by his bloode, the ſpirituall kingdome of his Church,<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 8. 1. Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> all the enemies thereof conquered. Whiche kingdome now he gouerneth<note n="c." place="margin">Ephe. 1.13 1. Cor. 6.19</note> by his woord, and by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb facs="tcp:171:22"/> whereby he raigneth in my hart, and in the hartes of his elect.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it teacheth that he was a<note n="d." place="margin">Heb. 5.5.6.7</note> prieſte to offer vp him ſelfe once for all, a ſwete ſacrifice, to take away my ſinnes, and to be a<note n="e." place="margin">Iohn. 14.13. Rom. 8.34</note> mediatour, by whom, and in whoſe name I may offer vp my prayers to God my heauenly father, and through him be heard.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, it putteth me in mynde that he was<note n="f." place="margin">Act. 3.21</note> a Prophet, ſent to preach the will of his heauenly father, whom<note n="g." place="margin">Math. 17.5.</note> alone I muſt heare and obey, as my Lord: who being thus appoynted of his father,<note n="h." place="margin">Mark. 14.10 &amp; .15.15.24 Iohn. 19.38.</note> was betraied of Iudas, condemned by Pilat, crucified by the Iewes, buried by Ioſeph of Aromathia and Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſuffred<note n="i." place="margin">Eſay. 53.4. Colloſ. 1.2.20.</note> in his bodie, not onely the puniſhmentes due to my body, but alſo<note n="k." place="margin">Math. 27.46.</note> in his ſoule, the puniſhmentes due to my ſoule, that was the very tormentes of hel and death, and ſeparation from God,<note n="l." place="margin">Rom. 5.19. Col. 2.14 1. Iohn. 3.8 Apoc. 20.14.</note> by whoſe death my obedience is wrought the malediction of Gods Lawe cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the Diuell, and his power ſubdued, the wrath of God appeaſed, and I ſet in his fauour agayne. And thus is the death of Chriſt, the onely and full raunſome for
<pb facs="tcp:171:22"/> my ſinnes, by vertue whereof, ſinne alſo dyeth and is killed in me.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="question">
               <head>44. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It is verie needefull to keepe this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent benefite alwayes in minde: tell me therefore, howe thou canſt medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the ſame aright.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Firſt<note n="a." place="margin">Iſay. 53 toto Rom. 4.25. Galat. 3.13 Ephe. 2.14.</note> I conſider, howe great the wrath of God was towarde my ſinnes, which coulde be appeaſed with nothing, but onelie with the deare bloudſhedding of his ſonne: and thereby, I beginne to hate and eſchewe ſinne euermore.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 3.16 &amp;, 10.17</note> herein I doo behold alſo the great loue of GOD,<note n="c." place="margin">Iohn. 4.10</note> whiche ſpared not his ſonne for my ſake, and likewiſe the great loue of his ſonne, that vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to doe ſo much for me.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, I<note n="c." place="margin">Gallat. 2.20.</note> applie and appropriate the ſame vnto my ſelfe, whatſoeuer Ieſus Chriſt herein hath done: for I am fullie aſſured, that he did it for me.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="question">
               <head>45. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What ſayeſt thou of his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>As he died for my ſinnes, ſo he roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne
<pb facs="tcp:171:23"/> for my iuſtification,<note n="b." place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.8.</note> hauing got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the victorie ouer ſinne, death, hell, and damnation, and geueth me power through his ſpirit,<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 8.10.11.</note> to riſe vnto newnes of life, aſſuring me, that my bodily death ſhalbe no deſtruction, but that I ſhall riſe againe at the laſt day, to life euerlaſting.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="question">
               <head>46. <hi>Queſtion</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Shewe thy minde of his aſcention.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>He aſcended<note n="a." place="margin">act. 1.9. and 3.21. Mat. 28.18.20.</note> with his bodie into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, where he remayneth, hauing all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer geuen him of his father, but with his ſpirite he is preſent with his people:<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 14.2. Tit. 2.5 Colloſ. 3.1.2.</note> by which his aſcention, he hath taken poſſeſſion for me in heauen, where he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo continueth a mediatour to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for me to his father, and finally, teacheth me to ſet mine affection vppon heauenlie thinges.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="question">
               <head>47. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What meaneſt thou by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to iudgement?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>I beleeue, that he which is my ſauiour<note n="a." place="margin">Mat. 24.31. 2. Theſ. 1.8.10. Luke. 21.35.</note> ſhal come to cleare me and all his elect in iudgement, and to condemne the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, which in their life time refuſed him,
<pb facs="tcp:171:23"/> to followe their pleaſures.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="question">
               <head>48. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What ſaieſt thou of the holy Ghoſt?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>I beleeue that<note n="a." place="margin">1. Cor. 6.11.</note> he is the ſpirit of ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification,<note n="b." place="margin">2. Cor 4.6.</note> geuen to lighten my mynde,<note n="c." place="margin">1 hn. 16.13</note> and to leade me into all trueth, he is<note n="d." place="margin">2 Cor. 1.22</note> the earneſt of mine inheritance in heauen,<note n="e." place="margin">Epheſ. 1.13.</note> the ſeale to imprinte Gods promiſes in my heart,<note n="f." place="margin">Iohn. 7.36. Eſay. 55.1</note> the fountaine of grace, and the water which purgeth me from mine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, and<note n="g." place="margin">Rom. 8.10.11.</note> maketh mee to die to ſinne, and to be holy vnto God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="question">
               <head>49. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Shewe thy minde concerning the Church.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare</head>
                  <p>The Church is<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 8.29. Epheſ. 1.4.10.11.</note> the ſocietie of all faithfull people, whom God in Chriſt hath choſen to ſaluation before the world was made, of<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 15.55</note> which number I beleeue that I am one.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="question">
               <head>50. <hi>Question.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What, is there no ſaluation without the Church?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>No,<note n="a." place="margin">Iohn. 16.4.</note> for as the branch, except it abide in the Vine, cannot bring foorth fruite,
<pb facs="tcp:171:24"/> but dyeth and withereth, and ſo is caſt into the fyre: euen ſo, except a man be graffed into the bodye of Chriſt, which is the Church, &amp; therein continue, he can not be ſaued. And therefore not euery re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhall ſaue the profeſſour thereof, but onely the truth of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="question">
               <head>51. <hi>Question.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What be the markes thereof.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a." place="margin">Iohn. 8.47. and. 10.27.</note>The ſincere woord of God,<note n="b." place="margin">Matth. 28.19</note> the right adminiſtration of the Sacraments,<note n="c." place="margin">Matth. 18.17 1. Cor. 5.1.</note> and Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline,</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="question">
               <head>52. <hi>Question.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Why is the Church called holy?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Becauſe God will haue his people to liue<note n="a." place="margin">Tit. 2.12.</note> holily, ſoberly, &amp; righteouſly in this world, and not<note n="b." place="margin">Epheſ 4.30</note> to greeue the holy Ghoſt by any vncleanneſſe, by whom they bee ſanctified, and by whom, whileſt they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelues to be led, they<note n="c." place="margin">Iohn. 16.13.</note> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not erre in matters of faith and ſaluation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="question">
               <head>53. <hi>Question.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I pray thee herein by the way, what thinkeſt thou of the church of Rome, whoſe doctrine hath bene receiued many yeares, hath ſhe erred and beene
<pb facs="tcp:171:24"/> deceiued.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>The Churche of Rome in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and long after the Apoſtles time, was a true Churche, and ſo long as ſhe followed<note n="a." place="margin">Iohn 14.16.17.</note> the worde of God, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her ſelfe to be guided with his ſpirite, ſhee was free from eroure in matters of faith.<note n="b." place="margin">1. Tit. 6.5. 2. Tit. 3.2. Apoc. 18.11.</note> But when ſhe began to abounde in wealth, ſhe forgate hir former huſband Chriſt Ieſus, and committed fornication with ſtraunge Gods,<note n="c." place="margin">Galat. 1.6.7.8. 2. Tit. 4.5. 2. Pet. 2.4.</note> leauing the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Chriſt and his religion, and deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a new worſhippe of her owne, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in<note n="d." place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.11. Apoc. 14.8.</note> according to the iuſt iudgement of God, ſhe floriſhed a long time, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall, polluted and made drounken the moſt part of the worlde, whileſt ſo many embraced her lawes and religion, yea, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen all thoſe whiche were not<note n="e." place="margin">Apoc. 7.3. &amp;. 13.8. &amp;. 17.5.</note> choſen to ſaluation, and ſealed by the ſpirit of faith.<note n="f." place="margin">2. Tit. 4.3.</note> And of this her departing from the faith, ſprang that great darkeneſſe, and ignoraunce of true religion in theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="question">
               <head>54. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What meaneth the communion of Saintes?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb facs="tcp:171:25"/>
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>It ſignifieth<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 12.5. 1. Cor. 12.12.</note> the felowſhippe which all the electe haue one with an other,<note n="b." place="margin">1. pet. 4.10. Galat. 6.2.</note> communicating according to the meaſure of faith, all ſpirituall graces amongeſt themſelues,<note n="c." place="margin">Epheſ. 4.3.</note> &amp; the ſtudying to keep the vnitie of the ſpirit in the bound of peace.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="question">
               <head>55. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What beleeueſt thou of the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Firſt, I beleeue that before my ſinnes be forgeuen me,<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 5.8.10. Epheſ. 2.1.2. 1. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r. 6.11.</note> there is nothing in me but meere wickedneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, I beleeue that al my ſinnes, and the puniſhment thereof bee taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way<note n="b." place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t. 2.4. Eſay. 53.5. 1. Cor. 1.30. 2. Cor. 5.21.</note> by Chriſtes death, and I made pertaker of his righteouſneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, I beleeue<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 3.25.</note> that faith alone, without anie worthineſſe of my ſelfe, doth make me partaker of theſe graces, and this my righteouſnes before God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="question">
               <head>56. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What ſayeſt thou of the reſt, the reſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the bodie, &amp; life euerlaſting?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>I beleeue when this life is ended, that<note n="a." place="margin">Eccle. 12.7. Apoc. 14.13. Luke. 16.22. Phillip. 1.23.</note> my ſoule ſhall goe to God, and my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,
<pb facs="tcp:171:25"/> to reſt in the earth til the laſt day, when they ſhall both ioyne together againe<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 15.53.</note> incorruptible, and remaine with God for euer in the kingdome of heauen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="question">
               <head>57. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Howe knoweſt thou, that thou haſt ſuche a faith as this?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Firſt, I knowe the ſame<note n="a." place="margin">Ro. 8.16.</note> by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the holie Ghoſt, which aſſureth my conſcience, that I am the childe of God, and whiche maketh me crie, Abba father, in ful and perfect aſſurance thereof.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, I knowe<note n="b." place="margin">Rom. 8.9.10. Gal. 2.20. Rom. 6. toto.</note> by the workes and fruites of faith, whiche Ieſus Chriſt being vnited and ioyned vnto me, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth in me, by the vertue of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, killing my corrupt and ſinfull nature and quickening me, to righteouſneſſe of life.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="question">
               <head>58. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Than cannot ſuch a faith as this bee fruiteleſſe, and without good workes.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>No, but good workes doe follow faith, as the<note n="a." place="margin">Mat. 7.17. Iacob. 2.24. 1. Pet. 1.12.</note> teſtimonies and fruites of my thankfulneſſe to God, whereby my faith is knowne, and approued of men:<note n="b." place="margin">Galat. 5.6.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:171:26"/> wherefore it is called faith, whiche wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth by loue.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="question">
               <head>59. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What workes muſt thou doe?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Suche as be commaunded me in the<note n="a." place="margin">Mat. 19.17.18.</note> lawe of God,<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 1.8. Epheſ. 2.10.</note> whiche as they come of grace geuen me, and not of mine owne power, ſo muſt they needes be done: for firſt<note n="c." place="margin">1. Pet. 1.16.</note> God hath ſo commaunded. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 6. toto. Tit. 2.14.</note> benefits bind me thereto. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note n="e." place="margin">Colos. 2.12.</note> my baptiſme doth teach me to die vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne, and liue vnto righteouſneſſe. Fourthly,<note n="f." place="margin">Mat. 5.16. 1. pet. 2.12.</note> I muſt glorifie God by my well doing. Laſt of all,<note n="g." place="margin">2. pet. 1.10.</note> I muſt make ſtrong my faith and election, and learne to auoyde the wrath of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="question">
               <head>60. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What rewarde ſhalt thou haue for thy good deedes?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>The woorkes, whiche I doe before I be iuſtified before God by Chriſt,<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 14.23. Heb. 11.6. Iohn. 3.36.</note> can not pleaſe him, becauſe they be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith. The workes which follow my regeneration,<note n="b." place="margin">Apoc. 7.14. Math. 25.40. Luke. 17.10. 1. Cor. 15.58.</note> doe pleaſe GOD, not becauſe of anie woorthineſſe of mine in them, but God accepteth them, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:171:26"/> of my faith in Chriſt, through whom they are not done in vaine, ſo that the rewarde which is geuen vnto them, commeth one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of<note n="c." place="margin">Apo. 22.</note> the free mercie and fauour of God whileſt he rewardeth not my deſerts, but crowneth his giftes of grace in me.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="question">
               <head>61. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>But the Scripture maketh mention often, of rewarde to good woorkes.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>It is true<note n="a." place="margin">Cor. 15.58. Luke. 17.10.</note> that my labour is not in vayne in the Lorde, yet my good workes are not ſuch, that of themſelues they can deſerue any ſuche thing. For there bee three thinges required to the nature of merites: Firſt, that the good woorkes be mans owne, for but to beſtowe and repay agayne the ſame which he had lent him, what rewarde can he haue. But as<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 4.7. Eph. 2.10. Luke. 16.2. &amp; 19.13.</note> for mans good workes, they be not his own, but the giftes of God lent him to vſe, &amp; he himſelfe Gods inſtrument to occupie the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it is required, that a man doe the worke of his owne accorde, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſtreint, or reſpect of duetie, for he that is bound to doe the ſame, cannot wel pleade of merite, for he doeth but what
<pb facs="tcp:171:27"/> of duetie he oughte to doe. But whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the righteous doe,<note n="c." place="margin">Pſal. 115.1. Rom. 8.12.</note> it is of duetie, for he is infinite wayes indebted vnto God. Thirdly, to the nature of deſeruing, it is required, that there be a iuſt proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betweene the thing giuen, and the thing receiued: but<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 8.18. Apoc. 22.17.</note> none of mans works are comparable to euerlaſting life. And therefore, I confeſſe, that I can not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue any thing of the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by mine owne works, for the reward which God geueth vnto my woorkes, is the free gift of grace, giuen to me onely for my faithes ſake in Chriſt, in whome my workes pleaſe God. Wherefore, yf man be neuer ſo vertuous in the ſighte of the world &amp; haue neuer ſo faire a ſhewe of good deedes, and not being graffed by fayth on Ieſus Chriſt, they are altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnfruitefull and vayne.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="question">
               <head>62. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>With what helpes doeth God fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thee to ſaluation?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Beſides that the worde of God,<note n="a." place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.3.</note> doth helpe to vphold my faith, the ſacraments and prayer are alſo helpes to me, for by them the Lorde helpeth mine infirmitie,
<pb facs="tcp:171:27"/> by<note n="b." place="margin">Mat. 28.19 1. Cor. 11.23. Geneſ. 11.17.</note> outwarde ſignes repreſenting to me ſpirituall graces.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="question">
               <head>63. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Doe the Sacramentes ſerue thee to anie other purpoſe?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>They ſerue not onely to<note n="a." place="margin">Exod. 12.11.12.13. Mat. 26.26. 1. Cor. 11.23.26. 1. Cor. 10.17.</note> teache me heauenlie thinges, but alſo to kindle a deſire of Gods promiſes in my heart, to ſtirre me vp to thankeſgeuing for my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, to knitte me in loue with the Godlie, and as markes of religion to teſtifie howe. I differ from the heathen and wicked. Wherefore, ſuch as refuſe to vſe the ſame, do<note n="b." place="margin">Mark. 8.38. Luk. 14.18.24.</note> not onlie denie God, but are alſo arrogant and proude. And therfore not to be accompted Chriſtians, becauſe they refuſe in vſing of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, to make open profeſſion thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="question">
               <head>64. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What is a Sacrament?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>It is an holy ſigne, inſtituted of<note n="a." place="margin">Mat. 21.25. Iohn. 3.5. Act. 2.38. Rom. 4.11.</note> God to confirme my faith, and to ſeale in my heart the promiſes of Gods mercie tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards me, for the forgiueneſſe of my ſinnes and ſaluation in Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="question">
               <head>65. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:171:28"/>
               <p>Whether doe the Sacraments geue grace to the receiuer, or no?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>They<note n="a." place="margin">Iohn. 1.33. Act. 8.18. 1. Cor. 10.5. Ro. 2.29. 1. Pet. 3.21</note> neither of themſelues nor in themſelues include or geue grace, for that is the gift of the holie Ghoſt, but they be holy ſignes, whereby, as by an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, God doth worke and ſeale grace in my heart by faith receiued, and yet they bee not bare or naked ſignes, but grace is truely preſent to my faith, when I receiue the ſame aright.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="question">
               <head>66. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Who ought to miniſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a." place="margin">Gen. 6.14. &amp; 17.23 Mat. 28.19.</note>None but ſuche as be miniſters too preach the woorde, for theſe two offices in the ſcriptures, concurre and goe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and therefore to none, but to ſuch as may lawfully miniſter the woorde, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteineth the miniſtring of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. And hereby women are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to miniſter baptiſme.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="question">
               <head>67 <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>How manie Sacramentes be there?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Two, the one is Baptiſme, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I am receiued into Chriſts church.
<pb facs="tcp:171:28"/> The other is the Supper of the Lorde, wherewith I am nouriſhed in the ſame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="question">
               <head>68. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What is Baptiſme?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>It is a Sacrament, wherein, as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter waſheth away the filthineſſe of my body, ſo<note place="margin">Act. 2.38 1. Pet. 3.21</note> the blood of Chriſt ſprinkled vpon my ſoule, by the hand of faith wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth away my ſinnes, and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, whereby<note place="margin">Rom. 6.5.</note> I am incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into his body, and made partaker of his benefites, to dye vnto ſinne, and to liue vnto righteouſneſſe, and this is the right vſe of baptiſme, that we be ſure that our conſcience be cleane, and that we ſhewe it to others by our good woorkes, in mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying our affections &amp; in doing the will of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="question">
               <head>69. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Why are children to be baptized?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Becauſe by<note n="a." place="margin">Ephe. 2.3. Rom. 5.12. Act. 2.39. Gen. 17.7</note> nature they be the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath, by Adams ſinne, to whom alſo the promiſe of Gods free mercy and fauour reacheth. So that being inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of Gods free graces, they muſt be baptized, and whan they come to age, be
<pb facs="tcp:171:29"/> inſtructed, what the meaning of baptiſme is.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="question">
               <head>70. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What is the Lordes Supper?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a." place="margin">Mat. 26.26.</note>It is a Sacrament of redemption dy the death of Chriſt, wherein by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall receiuing of breade and wine, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a true faith, I am made<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 10.16 Luke. 21.19. Iohn. 6.51.</note> pertaker of all the benefits of Chriſtes paſſion, for as bread broken doth feede and nouriſh my body, and wine refreſh my hart, ſo the<note n="c." place="margin">Luke. 22.19 Iohn. 6.51.</note> body of Chriſt was torne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe, and his blood ſhed, to waſhe away my ſinnes, and to feede and refreſh my ſoule, to life euerlaſting,</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="question">
               <head>71. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Whether is the bread chaunged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the natural body of Chriſt or no?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>The Sacramentes of bread and wyne<note n="a." place="margin">Mat. 26.29. Iohn. 6.51.53.5. 1. Cor. 10.16.17. &amp; 11.24.</note> remaine ſtill in their former nature and ſubſtance, neuertheleſſe there is a greate chaunge, for thoſe thinges which before were but as common meates, are nowe made the Sacramentes or holy ſignes of Chriſtes bodye and blood, <hi>b</hi> but ſo that we muſt ſeeke Chriſtes body in heauen,
<pb facs="tcp:171:29"/> and not in the Sacrament.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="question">
               <head>72. <hi>Question.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>How doeſt thou eate Chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or drinke his blood?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a." place="margin">Iohn. 6.35. Rom. 4.24.</note>Spiritually by grace, whileſt I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that he dyed for my ſinnes, and roſe againe for my iuſtification, for it is faith that maketh me pertaker of his benefits, and goodnes which are ſealed to me, by his Sacraments. And therefore by faith I am made one with him, for by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit he dwelleth in me, and is ioyned with me, as the heade with the members. So then by this coniunction, I may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of his graces.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="question">
               <head>73. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Do all men, which receiue this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, receiue the ſpirituall grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>As in baptiſme none<note n="a." place="margin">1. Pet. 3.21. Act. 2.38. &amp; 8.18. Marke. 16.16.</note> but the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full receiue remiſſion of their ſinnes,<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28.29.</note> ſo in the Lords ſupper, none but ſuch are pertakers of the grace, and benefittes of Chriſtes death. The wicked in deede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the outward elementes of breade and wine, but becauſe they lacke true
<pb facs="tcp:171:30"/> faith, they are not partakers of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall grace.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="question">
               <head>74. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Whither muſt thou once a yeare, as ſome doo of cuſtome, or often, come to the Lordes ſupper?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Although the benefit reſt not in the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, but in the worthy receiuing thereof, yet muſt I ſo often as I can conuenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, do the ſame, euer more and more to be thankefull for my redemption wrought by Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="question">
               <head>75. <hi>Question.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>How muſt thou frame thy ſelfe, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this Sacrament worthily?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Firſt I muſt<note n="a." place="margin">Mat. 26.75. Iere. 24.7 Ioel. 2.12.13. Rom. 6. toto.</note> conſider the greeuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my ſinnes, &amp; from my hart vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, hate and deteſt the ſame, and euer after geue my ſelfe to godlyneſſe and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Secondly,<note n="b." place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28. &amp; 2. Cor. 13.5.</note> I muſt try and examen my ſelfe, whether I haue a true faith in the promiſes of Chriſt. Thirdly,<note n="c." place="margin">Mat. 5.24 &amp; 22.39.</note> I I muſt reconcile my ſelfe to all men, and continue in Chriſtian loue.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="question">
               <head>76. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:171:30"/>
               <p>What thing is required, that thou mayeſt doo theſe thinges the better?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a." place="margin">Mat. 3.1. &amp; 26.21 Act. 31.14 &amp; 20.7. 1. Cor. 11.28 2. Par. 23.19</note>It is very expedient, that as in the primitiue Church the woord of God was preached before the adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Sacramentes, which thing is the life of the Sacrament, and alſo an examination taken of the communicantes, before the Lords ſupper was eaten: So is it I ſay, neceſſarie, that the woorde bee preached, and the people inſtructed in this miſtery, that they may ſhewe foorth the Lordes death vntill his comming againe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="question">
               <head>77. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Nowe remaineth the other helpe geuen thee of God, that is to ſay pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? Tell me what it is.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Prayer is the<note place="margin">Mat. 6.6. Iohn. 16.23. 1. Tit. 2.8.</note> lifting vp of my hart to God and aſking in Chriſtes name, of thinges needefull to mee and the whole Church,<note n="b." place="margin">Phillip. 4.6. Coloſ. 4.2.</note> with thankeſgeuing, for his benefites, and goodneſſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="question">
               <head>77. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>To whome muſt thou pray?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>To <hi>a</hi> God alone: firſt, becauſe I <hi>b</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue
<pb facs="tcp:171:31"/> in him alone.<note n="a." place="margin">Pſal. 50.15. Iohn. 16.33.</note> Secondly, he alone<note n="c." place="margin">1. Reg. 8.39.</note> knoweth my harte:<note n="b." place="margin">Rom. 10.14</note> thirdly,<note n="d." place="margin">Eſay. 42.8.</note> he will not geue his glory to any other, and therefore I am forbidden to pray to Saintes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="question">
               <head>79. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>How canſt thou, which art a ſinner, pray to God that hateth ſinne?<note n="a." place="margin">Ioh. 14.13.14. &amp; .16.23. Act. 4.12. 1. Tit. 2.5.6. 1. Iohn. 2.2.</note>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>I pray not in truſt of mine owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, but in the name of Chriſt, who is the<note n="b." place="margin">Iohn. 14.16.</note> way for me to come to the father, who<note n="c." place="margin">Rom. 8.34. 1. Tit. 2.5.6. 1. Iohn. 2.2.</note> continueth my Mediatour at the righte hande of the Father,<note n="d." place="margin">Iohn. 13.34.</note> loueth mee and hath<note n="e." place="margin">Coloſ. 1.22.</note> reconciled me to the Father,<note n="f." place="margin">Matt. 3.17.</note> and in whom the Father is well pleaſed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="question">
               <head>80. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>For whome muſt thou pray?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>For all men liuing, for<note n="a." place="margin">1. Tit. 2.1.2. Math. 5.44. Luke. 6.27.</note> kinges, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, miniſters, yea and for my eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: but for the deade I haue no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement to pray, neyther can I help them after they be gonne hence, for as they be found at the day of their death, ſo ſhall they riſe againe, onely this can I doe, to geue God thankes for their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance out of this world.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="question">
               <head>81. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:171:31"/>
               <p>How muſt thou prepare thy ſelfe to pray?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Firſt, I muſt<note n="a." place="margin">Rom. 8.26. 1. Iohn. 5.14.</note> be touched with the neceſſitie of thoſe thinges which I pray for, my minde muſt be deuout,<note n="b." place="margin">Mat. 6.7.</note> and not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to and fro with vaine thoughtes. I muſt appeare before God<note n="c" place="margin">Pſalm. 51.17. Iacob. 1.6.</note> in true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce and fayth,<note n="d." place="margin">Mat. 5.23.</note> being at loue with all men,<note n="e." place="margin">Eſay. 1.18. &amp; .59.2.</note> framing my life ryghteouſly, &amp;<note n="f." place="margin">1. Iohn. 5.14. 1. Cor. 14. toto. Mat. 6. Luke. 11.1.</note> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in ſuch a tongue as I vnderſtand, acording to the will of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="question">
               <head>82. <hi>Question.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>How muſt thou pray?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>According to the forme preſcribed of our Sauiour Chriſt, in theſe woordes: Our Father which art in heauen: hallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed be thy name. Thy kingdome come. Thy will be done in earth as it is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Geue vs this day our dayly breade. And forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that treſpas againſt vs. And lead vs not into temptation, but deliuer vs from euill. For thine is the kingdome, the power, and the glory, for euer, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. So be it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="question">
               <head>83. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:171:32"/>
               <p>What is the meaning of this praier?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare</head>
                  <p>We pray to God in the firſt petition that<note n="a." place="margin">pſal. 89.5.6 1. Cor. 10.31 Ioſu. 24.14.15</note> his glory may appeare, and that<note n="b." place="margin">Rom. 2.24.</note> our liues and conuerſation may ſet foorth the ſame. In the ſecond, we pray that God would<note n="c." place="margin">Iohn. 16.13. Rom. 8.10.11</note> gouerne the kingdome of his Church, killing ſinne, and the luſtes thereof in the ſame, and to renue it to ryghteouſneſſe of lyfe. That he would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<note n="d." place="margin">Rom. 16.20. 1. Iohn. 3.8.</note> treade downe Satan and al his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and that he would ſhortly<note n="e." place="margin">Apoc. 22.20.</note> accompliſh the number of his elect, and haſten the comming of Chriſt to iudgement. In the thirde we pray<note n="f." place="margin">Luke. 22.42</note> that all our dooings may be agreeable to his will, without contradiction or murmuring. In the fourth, we deſire him<note n="g." place="margin">Pſal. 14.1.15</note> to graunt vs what ſoeuer is needefull to the ſuſtenance and preſeruation of our lyfe, and that all our dooinges may be to his glorye, and the profit of our neighboures. In the fifth, wee praye<note n="h." place="margin">Pſal. 51.9 1. Iohn. 2.12. &amp; 18.35. Mat. 5.45.</note> for the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes and the puniſhment therof, for his mercies ſake, euen as we ſhall pardon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their offences doone to vs, without bearing mallice, or hatred towardes them.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:171:32"/>
                  <p>In the laſt wee praye that God<note n="i." place="margin">Epheſ. 6.10. Rom. 16.20.</note> would guyde vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſpirite, that we may get the victorie ouer Sathan, ſinne, and hell, and be defended from all euills. After we conclude with theſe woordes: For thine is the kingdome &amp;c. To ſet foorth our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to his glory, his honour, and prayſe, whoſe power is alſo infinite, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can graunt our requeſtes.<note n="k." place="margin">Ro. 11.36. Act. 4.9.11. Pſal. 114.7. 1. Chro. 29.10.</note> We make an end with this woorde, Amen, both deſiring, that what wee haue aſked may be fulfilled, and alſo aſſuring our ſelues, that our requeſtes ſhalbe fulfilled accordingly as they bee agreeing to the will of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="question">
               <head>84. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What if God do not graunt thy pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions at the firſt?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>That may be<note n="a." place="margin">Luke. 11.12. 1. Iohn. 5.14.</note> either becauſe I haue not aſked in aſſurance of faith and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of God, or els by differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the graunt of my requeſtes, he will trye and exerciſe my faith more in calling vpon him, that I might continue in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er &amp; depend vpon his mercifull goodnes, who notwithſtanding at the firſt he dooth not graunt my requeſtes, yet in his good
<pb facs="tcp:171:33"/> tyme he will accompliſh the ſame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="question">
               <head>85. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Is there any helpe for thee to praye more deuoutly?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Yea truly,<note n="a." place="margin">1. Pet. 5.11. Act. 13.3.</note> faſting is a ſpeciall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiue to the ſame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="question">
               <head>86. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What is a Chriſtian faſte?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>It is not onely an<note n="a." place="margin">Eſai. 58.3. Ioel. 2.12. Pſal. 35.13. Zach. 7.5.</note> abſtinence from meates, and drinkes, to chaſtice my body but alſo from ſinne and the delights ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which hurte the ſoule, to the end tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe true repentance, faith, Godly prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and renouncing of euyll, the Spirite may haue dominion in me.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="question">
               <head>87. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What is the right vſe of faſting?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a." place="margin">1. Cor. 9.27.</note>Firſt to chaſtice my body, and to bring it into ſubiection to the ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="b." place="margin">Ioel. 2.12.</note>Secondly, to be a witnes of my true repentance and ſubmiſſion to the will of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="c." place="margin">M 26.41.</note>Thirdly, that my ſpirit way be more ready to prayer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="question">
               <head>88. <hi>Queſtion</hi>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:171:33"/>
               <p>Is there any abuſe in the exerciſe of faſting?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Yea, many,<note n="a." place="margin">Eſai. 58.3. Zach. 7.5.</note> firſt to faſt longer then the body may endure, &amp; after to tare more deliciouſly. Secondly,<note n="b." place="margin">Coloſ. 2.16. Galat. 4.10. 1. Tit. 4.3.</note> to put holineſſe in faſting one day more than an other, or in abſtayning from one meate more than from another. Thirdly,<note n="c." place="margin">Eſai. 58.3. Rom. 3.24.</note> to thinke by faſting to purchaſe forgeuenes of ſinnes: whereas the ſame commeth onely of the free mercy of God in Chriſt, without any mannes woorthineſſe or deſeruing. Laſt of all in abſtayning from meates, &amp; not to<note n="d." place="margin">Galat. 5.24. Tit. 2.12.</note> abſtaine from ſinnes, and all thinges which cauſe or nouriſh the ſame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="question">
               <head>89. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Hitherto thou haſt anſweared verie well to all pointes of thy faith, yet one thing further I deſire to know, which is, why al men be not of this opinion in religion, that thou art of?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>Although there be but one true God,<note n="a." place="margin">Eph. 4.5.</note> and one perfect religion, yet muſt you not thinke that all men will euer agree toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one religion, for there<note n="b." place="margin">Gene. 5.13.</note> is and hath bene alwaies a continuall hatred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb facs="tcp:171:34"/> Chriſt the ſeede of the woman and the ſeede of the ſerpent. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many are profeſſed enemies to the way of truth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="question">
               <head>100. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>What way than thinkeſt thou beſt, to winne ſuch as be out of the way, and to bring them to the imbracing of true religion?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare.</head>
                  <p>As it is ſpecially required in building of an houſe, firſt to remoue away the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedimentes, and than to<note n="a." place="margin">Mat. 7.24. 1. Cor. 3.11.</note> lay a ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and afterward to vphold the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: likewiſe thoſe thinges which tend not to the glory of God,<note n="b." place="margin">2. Re. 18.44.</note> but which men haue abuſed muſt be rooted oute, as all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of papiſtrie &amp; ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; in ſtead therof a good foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> layd by the word of God,<note n="c." place="margin">Exod. 25.40. 1. Reg. 23.3.</note> by which all reformation muſt be made. Secondly,<note n="d." place="margin">1. Re. 2.35. Tit. 1.5. Prou. 11.14.</note> it is ſpecially re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, that a good and godlye preaching miniſter be placed in euery congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for where ſuch a one wanteth, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple periſh. Thirdly<note n="e." place="margin">Mat. 18.15. Act. 14.23. Rom. 12.8.</note> that there be a right and perfect vſe of eccleſiaſticall cenſure and correction, to the end the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be better kept in awe of duetie
<pb facs="tcp:171:34"/> and obedience, ſo that the beſt may be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to offend.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="101" type="question">
               <head>101. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>To be ſhort, dooſt thou thinke it ſufficient, onely to knowe theſe things aforeſaid?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſweare</head>
                  <p>No, but<note n="a." place="margin">Mat. 7.21. Phillip. 1.27. Coloſ. 1.23. Iacob. 1.22.</note> it is required, that I ioyne good lyfe and conuerſation with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and therefore I pray daiely that I may haue grace geuen me, that I maye liue godlily righteouſly and ſoberly, in this worlde, and ſo bee confirmed in the truth, that I may proceede from faith to faith, and be ſo comforted with the good ſpirit of God, that my whole delight may be repoſed, where true ioyes are to be ſought, that whan I ſhall finiſh this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal race, I may end the ſame in the faith and true profeſſion of Ieſus Chriſt my onely redeemer and ſauiour. To whom with the father and the holy ghoſt, three diſtinct perſons and one eternal God, be al glorie &amp; praiſe for euer. So be it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:171:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A prayer to be ſayde,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the receiuing of the Lordes Supper.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God, whiche of thine euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting kind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, haſte wroght our redemption by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of thy onely ſonne our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, and alſo ſealed the ſame vnto vs, for the more confirmation of our faith, by the heauenly and miſticall banquet of his laſt ſupper, inſtituted and ordeined as a pledge of his endles loue towardes vs, that we in vſing the ſame, from tyme to time might keepe a continuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of his death and paſſion, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie our thankefulneſſe for our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: We moſt humbly beſeeche thee in thy tender mercies to looke vpon vs, and to pardon vs all our iniquities, our incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie, and hardnes of hart, and to poure into vs thy heauenly grace, that wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:171:35"/> watred with the ſame, and purified by faith in thine euerlaſting promiſes, may be arayed and clothed with the excellent righteouſnes of Ieſus Chriſt, to the end hauing vpon vs our wedding garment, we may be welcome ghueſts, by thy grace, to thy holy table, Where our ſoules may be nouriſhed with the precious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of thy ſonne our Sauiours death and paſſion, and that we alſo through faith in the ſame, by thy grace may be fedde vnto immortallitie and lyfe. O Lorde wee beſeech thee to nouriſh and ſuſtaine our hungry ſoules, with the ſpiritual graces of thy ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch the thirſt of our harts, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the dew of thy holy ſpirit, that we may feele our ſinnes clearely to be forgiuen vs, and our conſciences aſſured by faith of all the benifites of thy ſonnes ſuffrings, euen ſo fully to be doone for vs, as if wee had doon the ſame our ſelues. Good Lord for his ſake, geue vs grace to proced from faith to faith, and more and more to bee confirmed in the way of our ſaluation, by the reuerent and godly vſe of theſe thy holy miſteries, giue vs a right iudgment and vnderſtanding thereof, and euer hold vs from all Popiſh corruptions of the
<pb facs="tcp:171:36"/> ſame, vnite vs more and more through thy grace vnto thy Sonne, that hee maye dwell in vs and wee in him, that he may be one with vs &amp; we with him to the end that being graffed and planted in him, we may be thankefull, and bring foorth the fruites of all holines of lyfe, to the honour and glory of thy holy name, through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord. So be it.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. Cor. 11.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> Let a man examen himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of this breade, and drink of this Cuppe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> For he that eateth and drinketh vnwoorthily, eateth and drinketh his owne damnation, becauſe he diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not the Lordes body.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:171:36"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>The forme of the</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Chriſtian faith, meete for all well <hi>gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned houſholdes, and</hi> neceſſarie for euery one to confeſſe, which ſincerely profeſſe Chriſt and his truth.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beleeue and confeſſe my Lorde God, the onely true, eternal and almightie God, inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, infinit, righteous, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, being but one in nature and ſubſtance, but diſtinct in three perſons, the father, ſonne and holie Ghoſt. Which God by his wiſedome and almightie power, made heauen and earth, and all thinges therein, and nowe by his fatherly prouidence, gouerneth and preſerueth the ſame.</p>
               <p>I beleue &amp; confeſſe that Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God, equall to the father and the holy Ghoſt, at the time appointed of the father, became perfect man, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne, borne of the virgin Mary, the Godhead and manhood being vnited and
<pb facs="tcp:171:37"/> ioyned together. Who in mine owne nature ſanctified by his grace, fulfilled the Lawe of God for me, and ſuffered in his body and ſoule, the puniſhmentes due to my ſinnes, and made full ſatiſfaction and payment for the ſame, with his ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vppon the croſſe, doone once for all. And deliuered me from the curſe of the Lawe, from ſinne, hell, death, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, reconciled me to God the Father, waſhed me from my ſinnes, cloathed me with his righteouſnes, and renued mee to righteouſnes of lyfe. And as by his death my ſinnes are taken away, and I ſet in the fauour God, ſo by his reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, death was conquered, and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe reſtored vnto me, wherein the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of my faith conſiſteth. I beleeue and confeſſe, that Ieſus Chriſt aſcended into heauen with my fleſhe, where he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for me, &amp; where he maketh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for me. And yet neuertheleſſe, is preſent with me, and all his elect, by his ſpirit and grace, and at the end of the world, ſhall viſibly come to iudgement.</p>
               <p>I beleeue the holy Ghoſt equall with the father and the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, who regenerateth and ſanctifieth me, from my vncleannes,
<pb facs="tcp:171:37"/> to liue holilie, and righteouſly in this worlde, aſſuring my conſcience, that I am the childe of God, and heire with Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt of life euerlaſting.</p>
               <p>I beleeue and acknowledge the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Church of Chriſt, euen al the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of the elect, agreeing together in the vnity of ſpirit and truth, which church is not ſeene to the eyes of man, but onely knowen to God, of which number I am perſwaded that I am one.</p>
               <p>I acknowledge alſo a viſible Church of God in this world, wherein firſt, the ſacred woord of God is taught vnto his people, being ſufficient to inſtruct them in all thinges neceſſarie to ſaluation. Wherwith together with the miniſterie of the ſpirit, he ruleth the ſame. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this Church, the two Sacramentes of Baptiſme and the Lords Supper are rightly and ſincerely miniſtred. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as by Baptiſme I am regenerate and receiued into the houſhold and felowſhip of Chriſtians, my ſinnes being waſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way through faith in Chriſtes blood: So by the Supper of the Lorde, wherein ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually by faith my ſoule is fed with the graces and benefits of Ieſus Chriſt I
<pb facs="tcp:171:38"/> am nouriſhed and ſuſtayned in the church being one with Chriſt, and Chriſt with me, dwelling alſo in him and hee in mee.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, there is in this Church due puniſhment and correction for offences, the end whereof is excommunication by the conſent of the Church.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, I beleeue and confeſſe, that onely in this Church there is ſaluation, and free forgiuenes of ſinnes to mee &amp; al the elect of God, through faith in Chriſt, by whoſe obedience we be made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and by whom we are choſen to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance immortall and euerlaſting in heauen. Which I moſt humbly beſeeche my Lord God to confirme and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then in me, and ſhortly to make an ende of theſe ſorrowful daies, &amp; to tranſlate me to euerlaſting glory, through Ieſus Chriſt my redeemer and Sauiour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>O Lorde increaſe our faith.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London, at the three Cranes in the Vintree, by Thomas Dawſon. (1579.)</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171:38"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
